{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "The Declaration of Independence said that this practice forced Americans “to become the executioners of their friends and Brethren.” This practice, designed to fulfill needs caused by the Napoleonic Wars, was one of the chief causes of the War of 1812. Thomas Jefferson signed the Embargo Act to combat this action after it occurred between the USS Chesapeake and HMS Leopard. For ten points, name this practice perpetrated by the Royal Navy to increase the number of its sailors.",
      "answer": "Impressment"
    },
    {
      "question": "This European tribe expanded into Dacia [[DAY-shuh]] during the Marcomannic Wars and to Pannonia during the Crisis of the Third Century. In 406, King Godigisel [[god- DIG-ih-sel]], leader of this tribe, died alongside 20,000 of his men while fighting against the Franks at the Battle of Mainz. According to Procopius, this tribe established a kingdom in North Africa in 429 at the request of Roman general Bonifacius. For ten points, name this Germanic tribe that sacked the city of Rome in 455 CE.",
      "answer": "Vandals"
    },
    {
      "question": "An early holder of this title in Russia, Avdotia Istomina, worked with Charles-Louis Didelot [[dee-deh-LOH]] during the Romantic period. The first major holder of this title in the United States, Maria Tallchief, was also the first indigenous woman to achieve this rank. This rank is higher than sujet [[soo-ZHAY]] or coryphée [[kor-ee-PHAY]], and is considered equivalent to the Premier Danseur Noble [[prem-YAY danh-SEUR NOH-bluh]] for men. For ten points, name this title held by Misty Copeland and Anna Pavlova, a term for excellent female performers in dance companies.",
      "answer": "Prima ballerina assoluta"
    },
    {
      "question": "This disease disproportionately affected males, and had notably high death rates in young adults. It is not polio, but some of the notable survivors of this illness were Walt Disney, Mahatma Gandhi, and Franklin Delano Roosevelt. Camp Devens in central Massachusetts was the site of the deaths of over 800 soldiers from this illness, and, along with the Boston Navy Yard, was responsible for spreading this pandemic’s second wave. For ten points, name this deadly global pandemic, which started during World War One.",
      "answer": "Spanish Flu or 1918 Influenza Pandemic 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Playoff Round 3"
    },
    {
      "question": "In an opera by this composer set during the California Gold Rush, Minnie loves the outlaw Dick Johnson. In another opera by this composer, the aria “E lucevan le stelle” is sung by Cavaradossi, who is awaiting his execution at the Castel Sant’Angelo. In an opera that this composer of The Girl of the Golden West left unfinished at his death, a Chinese princess says anyone who wants to marry her must answer three riddles. For ten points, name this Italian composer of “Nessun dorma” from Turandot [[TEWR-un-dot]], as well as Madama Butterfly.",
      "answer": "Giacomo Puccini"
    },
    {
      "question": "Princeton Psychology professor and eugenicist Carl Brigham helped design this product. James Conant and Henry Chauncey found “promising and talented individuals” using this product which was originally designed to create a \"racial caste system\" for race purity. In 2019, an \"Adversity Score\" based on factors like level of crime in a student's neighborhood was added to this exam. For ten points, name this College Board and ETS- developed college admissions exam, a competitor of the ACT.",
      "answer": [
        "Scholastic Aptitude Test",
        "SAT",
        "or Scholastic Assessment Test",
        "or SAT I: Reasoning Test"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This city hosted a 1992 UN convention on climate change. In 1864, Hamaguri rebels razed 28,000 houses in this city, resulting in a governmental reorganization, a decline of the local economy, and the construction of the Lake Biwa Canal. During World War Two, US Secretary of War Henry Stimson insisted that this city be removed from a list of bombing targets due to its cultural significance. For ten points, name this former imperial capital of Japan.",
      "answer": "Kyoto"
    },
    {
      "question": "This person's painting, \"Yucca and Cactus,\" was shown at the 1893 Columbian Exposition. This innovator’s \"bulletins\" helped farmers grow crops like cotton and sweet potatoes. This man combatted boll weevil infestation through crop rotation, which led Time magazine to give him the nickname, the \"Black Leonardo.” At an Alabama institution, this man pioneered products like antiseptic hair dressing made from peanut oil. For ten points, name this inventor who worked at Tuskegee Institute.",
      "answer": "George Washington Carver"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man was sentenced to eight years of hard labor for criticizing Josef Stalin in a private letter. This man’s experience at Ekibastuz formed the basis for One Day in the Life of Ivan Denisovich. Although Khrushchev’s reforms freed this man from exile in 1956, the publication of his Cancer Ward and other works provoked the Soviet Union to revoke this man’s citizenship in 1974. For ten points, name this Russian Nobel Prize winner and author of The Gulag Archipelago.",
      "answer": "Aleksandr Solzhenitsyn 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Playoff Round 3"
    },
    {
      "question": "In 773, this man led a campaign against the Saxons, during which he forced the Engrians to tear down the pagan Irminsul pillar and convert to Christianity. Upon this man’s death and burial at Aachen, his son Louis the Pious took the throne. Pope Leo III rejected the legitimacy of Empress Irene of Constantinople when he crowned this man Imperator Romanorum at St. Peter’s Basilica in 800. For ten points, name this man, who in 768 became King of the Franks following the death of Pepin the Short.",
      "answer": [
        "Charlemagne",
        "Charles the Great"
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man became chairman of SNCC [[SNIK]] in 1963, after which James Forman rewrote a speech by this man to read, \"We support [the Kennedy civil rights bill] with great reservations.” This man was the first of the Freedom Riders to be attacked while at Rock Hill and accused Julian Bond of using cocaine en route to being elected to the House. As one of the \"Big 6\" in the March on Washington, this man led the Selma to Montgomery Marches, being attacked on Bloody Sunday. For ten points, name this Civil Rights leader from Georgia who passed away in 2020.",
        "answer": "John Lewis"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "John Lewis was succeeded as Chairman of SNCC [[SNIK]] by this man, a fellow Freedom Rider, who later became \"Honorary Prime Minister\" of the Black Panthers, moved to Africa, and changed his name to Kwame Ture.",
        "answer": "Stokely Carmichael"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Eastern bishops met when this man called the Second Council of Constantinople which condemned the idea that Mary was the Mother of God. This man closed the Neoplatonic Academy and abolished the worship of Amun. The first plague pandemic is named for this man, and two monks smuggled silkworms from Central Asia back to this man's empire. Under this man, Isidore of Miletus and Anthemius of Tralles had the Hagia Sofia constructed. This emperor faced the Nika riots and was married to Empress Theodora. For ten points, name this Byzantine Emperor.",
        "answer": [
          "Justinian I",
          "Justinian the Great"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Nika Riots stemmed from disagreements among four factions that grew up in Constantinople, all wearing different colors and supporting different teams in which sport?",
        "answer": "Chariot racing"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A Jewish tribe identified as the Banu Qurayza betrayed this city during the Battle of the Trench. One document signed in this city defines a community identified with the term ummah. This city is home to the Green Dome, which is part of the last mosque built by Muhammad, the Prophet's Mosque. This city was the destination of a group of early Muslims fleeing their hometown in a trip known as the hegira. For ten points, name this second- holiest city in Islam, the location to which Muhammad fled from Mecca.",
        "answer": "Medina or Al Madinah Al Munawwarah"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Medina is home to the tombs of Mohammed, Umar, and this other caliph, a father in-law of Muhammad, considered the first Caliph by Sunnis.",
        "answer": "Abu Bakr al Siddiq or Abu Bakr Abdullah ibn Uthman 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Playoff Round 3"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "China gave this country 15 thousand military advisers and a $20 million gift to help its communists. This country invaded its neighbor in the Ba Chúc massacre, causing the collapse of a regime. Both GRUNK and FUNK operated in this country, and supporting Operation Freedom Deal in this country led the US to adopt the War Powers Resolution. In this country, the “new people” were eliminated by the “base people,” and its government operated the Santebal in its Killing Fields. For ten points, the Khmer Rouge and Pol Pot governed which country?",
        "answer": [
          "Kingdom of Cambodia",
          "Democratic Kampuchea",
          "Khmer Republic",
          "People's Republic of Kampuchea"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This man ruled Cambodia as its king twice, from 1941 to 1955 and from 1993 until he abdicated in favor of his son in 2004.",
        "answer": "Norodom Sihanouk Both names required"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man's wife was the Russian ballerina Lydia Lopokova, and his brother injected radium chloride to fight breast cancer tumors. This man proposed a logical-relationist theory of probability in a 1921 treatise. This man introduced the ideas of the consumption function while denying that the economy would adapt to give full employment, instead believing in booms and panics. This author wrote The General Theory of Employment, Interest and Money. For ten points, name this English economist who opposed Classical Economics.",
        "answer": [
          "John Maynard Keynes",
          "1st Baron Keynes"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Keynes coined the term for this law which states that production is the source of demand. It is named for a Frenchman who studded entrepreneurial economics.",
        "answer": "Say's Law"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man's decision on stare decisis led to a split into strong and weak forms after Burnet v. Coronado Oil & Gas Co. In Gilbert v. Minnesota, this man defended Freedom of Speech, and he aided Thomas Masayrk's Washington Declaration. The Judiciary Committee held its first ever public hearing for this man, and this man's pioneering legal brief style featured expert witness testimony and scientific information which was used in Muller v. Oregon. For ten points, name this first Jewish Supreme Court Justice.",
        "answer": "Louis Brandeis"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Brandeis was born in Louisville, Kentucky to parents who came to the US from Bohemia, a region that is now part of this modern-day country.",
        "answer": "Czech Republic or Czechia 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Playoff Round 3"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The so-called “second generation” of this art movement included three founders of the Metropolitan Museum of Art: John Frederick Kensett, Sanford Robinson Gifford, and Frederic Edwin Church. The towns of Skaneateles and Catskill both host historic landmarks dedicated to this art movement, which is named after a nearby location. For ten points, name this mid-19th century American art “school” exemplified by the landscape art of Thomas Cole and Asher Durand.",
        "answer": "Hudson River School"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Perhaps the best known Hudson River School painting is this Asher Durand work that depicts Thomas Cole and his friend, William Cullen Bryant in the Catskills.",
        "answer": "Kindred Spirits"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This house was founded by John of Fond Memory, and one of this house's rulers governed as Peter the Constable. António, Prior of Crato, tried to lead this house, though he lost the Battle of Ponta Delgada. This house's members included Ferdinand the Holy Prince who, as part of the \"illustrious Generation,” attacked Tangier with his brother, Henry the Navigator. The last ruler of this house was followed by a union with Spain under Philip II. For ten points, name this Portuguese house.",
        "answer": [
          "House of Aviz",
          "Joanine Dynasty"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "John II, of the House of Aviz, worked with Spain to separate their New World discoveries from Portugal's through this 1494 treaty.",
        "answer": "Treaty of Tordesillas"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Wells Fargo and the West",
      "prompt": "In the history of Wells Fargo in the Western United States, name the…...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Mail service utilizing horses that Wells Fargo controlled from 1860 to 1861.",
          "answer": "Pony Express"
        },
        {
          "question": "California state capital with Wells Fargo's second office.",
          "answer": "Sacramento"
        },
        {
          "question": "Communication method using Morse Code that hurt Wells Fargo's transportation services.",
          "answer": "Telegraphy"
        },
        {
          "question": "Type of horse-drawn vehicle Wells Fargo utilized to control western transportation.",
          "answer": "Stagecoach"
        },
        {
          "question": "American credit card giant that Wells and Fargo founded.",
          "answer": "American Express or AMEX"
        },
        {
          "question": "Company that built the transcontinental railroad with Union Pacific, whose Pacific Union Express was acquired by Wells Fargo.",
          "answer": "Central Pacific Railroad"
        },
        {
          "question": "New York city for which William Fargo served as mayor during the Civil War.",
          "answer": "Buffalo"
        },
        {
          "question": "Company joined with Wells Fargo and Overland in the Western mail “grand consolidation.”",
          "answer": "Holladay 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Playoff Round 3"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "The Árpád Dynasty",
      "prompt": "Name the…...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Country the Árpád Dynasty ruled with its modern capital at Budapest.",
          "answer": "Hungary"
        },
        {
          "question": "Along with the Tisza, Sava and Drava, this “Blue” river is one of the four Árpád stripes.",
          "answer": "Danube River"
        },
        {
          "question": "This king of the Premyslids succeeded the final Árpád ruler and shares his name with a “good” king in a Christmas carol.",
          "answer": [
            "Wenceslaus III",
            "Ladislaus"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Saintly first king of the Árpáds who shares his name with the first Christian martyr.",
          "answer": "Saint Stephen I"
        },
        {
          "question": "Group that devastated Árpád rule, including at Mohi, led by Subutai.",
          "answer": [
            "Mongols",
            "Golden Horde"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "955 Battle before the dynasty began in which Otto the Great defeated Lel and Sur.",
          "answer": "Battle of Lechfeld"
        },
        {
          "question": "Last king of the Árpáds, a man called “the Venetian.”",
          "answer": "Andrew III"
        },
        {
          "question": "Scottish clan in the parish of Dryman that claims descent from George, the son of an Árpád king.",
          "answer": "Drummond 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Playoff Round 3"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Uruguayan Independence",
      "prompt": "Name the......",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Capital of Uruguay, occupied by Britain in 1807.",
          "answer": "Montevideo"
        },
        {
          "question": "Portuguese-speaking country, ruled by Pedro I, that claimed the Cisplatine Province, now Uruguay.",
          "answer": "Empire of Brazil"
        },
        {
          "question": "Estuary of the Uruguay and Paraná Rivers, on the border of Argentina and Uruguay.",
          "answer": "Rio de la Plata"
        },
        {
          "question": "Leader of the Italian legion, a \"Hero of the Two Worlds\" who helped Uruguay and helped unify Italy.",
          "answer": "Giuseppe Maria Garibaldi"
        },
        {
          "question": "Opponent party of the Colorados, headed by President Manuel Oribe.",
          "answer": [
            "Blancos",
            "Whites"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "War in which Uruguay teamed up with Argentina to beat Francisco Solano López.",
          "answer": [
            "Paraguayan War",
            "War of the Triple Alliance"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Argentine dictator who was attacked in the Great War and operated the Mazorca secret police.",
          "answer": "Juan Manuel de Rosas"
        },
        {
          "question": "Father of Uruguay, who beat the Spanish at Las Piedras and formed the League of the Free Peoples.",
          "answer": "José Gervasio Artigas 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Playoff Round 3"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A 340-symbol cipher created by this person was deciphered in 2020 by a team including mathematicians and software engineers. Fifty-one years earlier, a 408- symbol cryptogram created by this person was cracked by Donald and Bettye (20 pts)",
        "Harden who determined that it included a reference to “The Most Dangerous Game.” That puzzle was in a collection of letters sent by this person to three (10 pts)",
        "newspapers in 1969, taking credit for a series of California shootings. For ten points, name this still- unidentified serial killer who signed those letters with a crossed circle."
      ],
      "answer": "Zodiac Killer"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The Iron Age kingdom of Fortriu is synonymous with this tribe. By the year 900, this tribe merged with the Gaelic kingdom of Dal Riata to form the Kingdom of Alba, which by the 13th century had expanded to include the formerly Brittonic kingdom of (20 pts)",
        "Strathclyde. This tribe’s eponymous monumental stele [[STEE-LEE]] were created between the 6th and the 9th centuries, the period of this tribe’s conversion to Christianity. Located north of the rivers (10 pts)",
        "Forth and Clyde, the Ptolemy world map calls this tribe the Caledonii. For ten points, name this Early Medieval Scottish people."
      ],
      "answer": "Picts"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man asserted a reaction-diffusion theory of morphogenesis in his namesake patterns, which explain why nature has stripes, spots, and spirals. This man developed a sequential analysis technique in statistics that measures evidence using (20 pts)",
        "“bans.” The highest prize that the ACM offers is named for this man, whose namesake test determines if a machine is (10 pts)",
        "sufficiently intelligent. This man developed a bombe device to decrypt the Enigma machine. For ten points, name this British mathematician who modeled computation with his namesake machine."
      ],
      "answer": "Alan Turing"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The first edition of this book contained 200 selected quotations across 23 topics, including “Correcting Mistaken Ideas,” “The Mass Line,” and “Political Work.” An endorsement in this book’s second edition was removed in 1971 after the endorser died in a (20 pts)",
        "Mongolian plane crash and was labeled a traitor. Until the later years of its author’s rule, each (10 pts)",
        "Chinese citizen was required to carry a copy of this book at all times, and it is commonly cited as one of the most published books in history. For ten points, name this book, a collection of statements by Mao Zedong."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "The Little Red Book",
        "Quotations from Chairman Mao Zedong or Mao Zhuxi Yulu 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Playoff Round 3"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Don Antonio Coronel told this woman about Mission Indians, and she was recommended as an agent by Hiram Price. After a lecture on the removal of the Ponca in Nebraska by Standing Bear, this woman started targeting federal officials like Interior Secretary Carl (20 pts)",
        "Schurz. A Scottish-Native American orphan named Ramona was created by this author, who also told seven tribal histories in (10 pts)",
        "A Century of Dishonor. For ten points, name this poet, author, and activist for Native Americans."
      ],
      "answer": "Helen Hunt \"H.H.\" Jackson"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In this year, Norfolk, Virginia was burned and looted on New Year’s Day. Chatterton Hill was taken in this year at the Battle of White Plains. In this year, Richard Caswell led the Patriots in the Battle of Moore's Bridge, and John Sullivan helped defeat the forces of Johann (20 pts)",
        "Rall at a battle in this year. At McConkey's Ferry in this year, Henry Knox and George Washington (10 pts)",
        "crossed the Delaware River. The Battle of Trenton occurred in, for ten points, what year, which featured the ringing of the Liberty Bell and signing of the Declaration of Independence."
      ],
      "answer": "1776"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This person studied Native American cultures through the lens of \"Apollonian\" and \"Dionysian\" viewpoints. This author worked with Gene Weltfish to write a pamphlet analyzing how brain size does not impact intelligence titled \"The Races of (20 pts)",
        "Mankind.” Another of this woman's works explains why Japanese POWs did not try to contact their families and explains Japan's (10 pts)",
        "\"shame\" culture in contrast with American \"guilt\" culture. For ten points, name this anthropologist who wrote The Chrysanthemum and the Sword."
      ],
      "answer": "Ruth Fulton Benedict"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This person was almost freed in the Carnation Plot, foiled by the incorruptibility of the guards. This person was jailed as Prisoner Number 280 in the Conciergerie. Once called the \"Widow Capet,” this woman's son was given (20 pts)",
        "to the cobbler Antoine Simon. Edme-Bonaventure Courtois found this person's will among Robespierre's papers. With her reputation damaged in the (10 pts)",
        "Affair of the Diamond Necklace, this woman was guillotined after her husband. This person likely never said, \"Let them eat cake.” For ten points, name this Queen of France, the wife of Louis XVI."
      ],
      "answer": "Marie Antoinette 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Playoff Round 3"
    }
  ]
}